Walking through these busy streets in today's Amsterdam, it's easy to forget the events that took place in these few short city streets during World War II.
If we look closely, we can uncover some of the memories and the heartbreak of the Jewish people who lived and walked these streets, and the devastation that was inflicted upon
the entire community. We are at the Waterlooplein here, the centre of Jewish life before the war. The outdoor market here was one of the
only ones open on Sundays, and frequented by many Amsterdammers. Across from the Waterlooplein we can see the Portuguese Synagogue,
a large, imposing building built in 1675.
When Jews were forced to leave Spain and Portugal, many found their way to Amsterdam, where the newly formed Dutch Republic guaranteed some form of religious tolerance and
economic opportunity. The community grew further during the 17th century, as many Jews from Central and Eastern Europe fled the attacks
of pogroms. The Great Synagogue you see across the street, also built in the 1670s, now houses the Jewish Historical Museum.
Because of the religious tolerance guaranteed by the Dutch Republic, and later the Kingdom of the Netherlands, the community enjoyed safety from persecution,
often prospering and numbering about 115,000 people by the 1930s. During the 1930s, about 25,
000 German and Austrian Jews sought refuge in the Netherlands from persecutions in their own countries. Most of the Jewish population in the Netherlands, about 85,
000 lived in Amsterdam. The Netherlands seemed to offer a safe haven, and having stayed neutral during World War One, when war broke out in Europe in
1939, the Netherlands hoped they would remain out of it. This was not to be so. A bit of background information: the
German army carried out a surprise attack using blitzkrieg tactics on the neutral Netherlands on May 10th, 1940, and after five days of fighting
and the aerial bombing of Rotterdam on May 14th, the Netherlands surrendered, and the five-year occupation by the Nazis followed. Very little changed for most Dutch
people during the first few months of occupation, but things would quickly become different — especially for Dutch Jews. Government workers had been forced to
sign an Aryan declaration, stating that they had no Jewish grandparent. This was the first of the measures aimed at isolating the Jewish population from the
rest of Dutch society. In January of 1941, all persons having any Jewish ancestor had to register with the city and pay
one guilder to do so. In May 1941, once people were registered, the local Bureau of Statistics was instructed by the Germans to create
a map putting a black dot on the map which indicated that 10 Jewish people lived there. The Netherlands had a fascist party based on the ideals of
Hitler and the Nazis, called the NSB. Some party members, like the German Nazis, formed a uniformed unit who, shortly after occupation began,
began harassing Jewish citizens and businesses. They were often confronted by informal militias composed of both Jews and non-Jews.
Sometimes these clashes were extremely violent. The German occupation police force, the Grüne Polizei, or Green Police,
was responsible for dealing with any unrest. In February 1941, during one of these disturbances, an NSB man was mortally wounded.
After his death, the Jewish Council was set up in Amsterdam to carry out anti-Jewish measures set by the Nazi occupiers.
NSB uniformed groups continued to march around the city in a show of force, trying to provoke a reaction. On February 19th, a skirmish took place at
an ice-cream parlour called Koco. The Jewish owners sprayed the Green Police with an ammonia canister. Shots were fired by the police, and the
owners and other Jewish customers were arrested. In Nazi Germany, the SS leader Heinrich Himmler, along with the SS chief and head of police in the Netherlands,
ordered immediate retaliation. The area right here in front of the Portuguese Synagogue was the site of this first razzia,
or raid, in Amsterdam. Starting Saturday morning, February 22nd, the area was sealed off by opening bridges to prevent
anyone from fleeing, and 427 Jewish men between the ages of 18 and 35 were rounded up by the Green Police at gunpoint.
They were forced to kneel on this square with their hands in the air, and suffered further humiliations until they were loaded into waiting
vans, often beaten with rifle butts. Most of these men eventually ended up in the concentration camp Mauthausen,
where all but two were murdered. Otto Frank, Anne's father, witnessed the scene and immediately started preparing a place for his family to hide.
Many other non-Jewish Amsterdammers witnessed these scenes as well. The Sunday market was always a busy one, and they were shocked by the brutal
treatment by the occupation forces. A local branch of the Communist Party then decided to organise a strike. They distributed thousands of flyers
which read: 'Strike! Show solidarity with the Jewish part of our society, which has been hit so hard.' Tram workers were the first to strike,
sanitation crews, dock workers, shipyard workers — all left their workplaces to join the strike. Department stores and other shops and businesses closed their doors,
teachers and students left their classrooms, until about 300,000 people in Amsterdam and other large cities
were striking. The German occupation was completely taken by surprise, and responded with force. 'No strikes in
the Third Reich,' is what they said. They broke the strike, killing nine participants and wounding many others. People were arrested, some were deported,
and eventually executed. This strike is the only instance of a general strike in all of occupied Europe that protested the anti-Jewish measures.
The statue you see — of a man standing tall and proud — represents the power of the ordinary working class against that of the oppressor. Each year
in February, a memorial service is held here. More anti-Jewish measures followed quickly, with the Jewish Council being
responsible for informing the population of each measure. By September 1941, Jewish children had to attend separate
schools, and all public accommodations such as parks, swimming pools and sports fields were forbidden. In January 1942, a large 'J' was added
to a Jewish identity card. On May 3rd, 1942, it became mandatory for Jews six years and older to wear a yellow Star of David
on the left side of any visible clothing. Four stars were made for each Jewish person — almost 570,000 in all. You had to buy the stars
at four cents each, and turn in a ration ticket for textiles as well. If you were caught not wearing the star, you could be fined a thousand guilders
or get six months in prison — but what actually happened is that you would be deported to a concentration or extermination camp.
Walking along the canal and just beyond the Botanical Gardens is a street called the Plantage. The buildings on this street witnessed some of the most difficult
moments for the Jewish population of Amsterdam. The Hollandsche Schouwburg, the Dutch Theatre, was one of many theatres in Amsterdam before the war.
As the area became more and more isolated and designated as a Jewish neighbourhood, the theatre was renamed the Joodsche Schouwburg, or Jewish
Theatre, and for a time saw a variety of performances by Jewish artists with a Jewish audience. But these performances ended
in 1942. In June of 1942, the Jewish Council was told to issue 4,000 call-up papers for forced labour in
Germany. Margot Frank, Anne's sixteen-year-old sister, received her call-up papers on July 5th, and the family went into hiding on July 6th.
It was then decided that the Hollandsche Schouwburg would be used as a holding place, where people reported and before they were taken to trains
to be sent first to Westerbork, the large transit camp in the north, and eventually to concentration and extermination camps in Germany and
Eastern Europe. Conditions were really pretty awful at the Hollandsche Schouwburg. Often up to 300 people were held as they
waited for days, or even sometimes weeks, to be transported further. There were limited toilets and washing facilities. People sat on the floor of the theatre
after the seats were removed, sometimes on the steps or upstairs in the balcony. There was a small spot outdoors where people could get some fresh air and walk around a bit.
This is a picture of Freya Fellaini, a 17-year-old Jewish girl waiting for transport. The picture was taken by a friend of hers, Lydia, a non-Jewish girl
who lived in the apartment building overlooking the back of the theatre. They waved to each other; Lydia took the picture, but never saw Freya again.
Walter Süskind, who held both German and Dutch nationality and spoke both languages fluently, was placed in charge of the Hollandsche Schouwburg by the
Jewish Council. Early on, it was decided that children under the age of 12 would be taken to a Jewish nursery across the street from the theatre.
A plan then evolved to try to save as many children as possible. Two doors away from the children's nursery was a teachers' college, but in the rear, the gardens of the
nursery and the teachers' college were adjacent to one another. Süskind, along with several others including Henriëtte Pimentel, in charge of the nursery, and Johan
van Hulst, director of the teachers' college, devised a plan to save as many children as possible. Süskind would take some children's names
off the lists, sometimes reporting them as having taken ill and died. Sometimes mothers of infants would be given an empty blanket to take with them
on the train to Westerbork. And sometimes families with several children would just have the number changed — from four to two, for example. Parents would, of course, have to agree,
knowing they might never see their children again, and not knowing where they would be going. Safe homes also had to be found for the children, usually in farming villages in
the east and north of the Netherlands. But how would all of this be accomplished? If you were standing in front of the theatre, you can see two rows of tram tracks, and
trams stop at regular intervals right outside the theatre. When two trams stop at the same time, it's virtually impossible to see what's going on
on the other side of the street. There were guards stationed in front of the theatre, but no one guarded the nursery. Children would be lifted over the back garden hedge from the nursery to the
college. Babies would be put in suitcases or bags after they were given something to make sure they slept and were quiet, and the students at the college, many of
whom worked with the resistance, would then simply walk right out of the building and get on a tram, carrying their bags. Older children would sometimes have the stars removed
from their clothing, and they would just walk onto a tram with a student. Sometimes older children would be taken for walks in groups, and one child would be told to walk at
the back of the line, where they would be met by a so-called cousin who would simply walk off in a different direction with them. It is estimated that between 600 and a
thousand children were saved in this way. By the fall of 1943, after approximately 80,000 Jewish people had passed through
the Hollandsche Schouwburg, the doors of the theatre and the nursery were closed, and all those remaining — including Süskind and Pimentel — were sent to Westerbork.
Neither one of them survived the war. In the entrance hall to the Hollandsche Schouwburg is an eternal flame, which burns in front of a wall
of the 6,700 family names of all the Jewish people who were deported from the Netherlands, never to return. Where the theatre seats
used to be is now an open space with a large monument in the shape of the Star of David. Just down the street is the building which housed the civil
registration office. In 1943, several members of the resistance carried out an attack on this building in order to try and destroy the records
which provided names and addresses of Jewish citizens to the Nazis. It would also help prevent them from identifying false
documents. Because six of the nine resistance members were artists who were involved in creating these false papers, the other three were medical students.
On the night of March 27th, dressed in police uniforms, the group told the security guards they needed to search the building for explosives.
The guards believed their story and let them in. The medical students then drugged the guards and carried them out a back door, while the others piled up all the documents on the floor,
soaking them with benzene and setting off a series of explosions, setting the building ablaze. The fire department had also been tipped off and
took their time arriving. And when they did arrive, they flooded the building with water, hoping to further damage any records.
In total, about 800,000 identity cards were destroyed — unfortunately, only about 15% of the total.
One of the resistance members had bragged about the action and was tracked down by the Nazis. In his notebook, more information was found about the attack.
Many resistance members were then caught, and twelve of them were executed shortly after, on the same street
as Artis, Amsterdam's zoo and the oldest zoo in Europe. Artis, like all public parks and places, was forbidden for Jews from September 1941 onwards.
The German soldiers loved visiting the zoo, enjoying the animals and nature right in the middle of the city of Amsterdam. What they never knew was that Artis provided shelter
for many Amsterdammers trying to avoid capture. Jewish citizens were not the only ones who tried to avoid falling into the clutches of the German occupation.
In May 1943, it was announced that all men between the ages of 18 and 35 had to register to be sent as forced labour to Germany.
Eventually, these men totalled about half a million workers. Many of them went into hiding to avoid being sent to Germany.
Artis provided a hiding place for between 200 and 300 men, sometimes for days, sometimes for weeks. No one knows exactly how many or for how
long. There was a plank which could be placed over the water leading to the monkey enclosure, and when there was a raid, men would quickly cross it to hide within the
rock-like structure. Artis also provided a safe haven for several Jewish people and resistance members. Dora van den Brink was a Jewish woman
who hid in Artis for four years. Every morning she would just walk around the zoo like all the other visitors, sitting on a bench outside the monkey
enclosure, talking to other visitors, including many of the German soldiers. She spent her nights sleeping in the wolf enclosure. Just a
block away from the zoo is a small car park called the Wertheimpark. Walking towards the park you might look down and see several
brass squares on the ground. These are inscribed with the names and life dates of victims of Nazi persecution. It is a project by a German artist named
Gunter Demnig. They are called Stolpersteine, or stumbling stones, and are placed in front of houses all over Europe,
now totalling over 75,000 stumbling stones. Wertheimpark houses the Mirror Memorial. This memorial was created by Dutch
writer and artist Jan Wolkers in memory of the many victims of Auschwitz. The monument is made up of broken mirrors covered by a solid glass plate.
The standing glass wall behind it reads: 'Never again Auschwitz'. According to the artist, the memorial reflects the sky through broken mirrors,
because the sky will never be the same after Auschwitz. Under the monument is an urn containing the ashes from the extermination camp Auschwitz.
Walking back towards the Waterlooplein, we see the modern building complex which now houses the city hall, opera house and ballet theatre. Thousands of people walk here
every day, but most do not see the rectangle of grey bricks that juts out. These stones outline the building of the Jewish boys' orphanage that stood here,
and on those stones are written the words: 'From here, almost 100 children, and their caretakers who voluntarily remained with them,
were taken in March 1943. All were sent to the extermination camp Sobibor; none survived.' This final monument at the
bend of the Amstel river is a memorial to the Jewish members
of the resistance.